# Li Ding

☐ liding256@gmail.com

**♦** Mountain View, CA

https://liding.info

SUMMARY

My research focuses on aligning AI systems with human values and enable safe, self-directed agent learning in open-ended environments. I developed methods using reinforcement learning from human feedback (RLHF) to enhance the safety, creativity, and generalization of AI agents and large language models (LLMs).

#### **EDUCATION**

# **University of Massachusetts Amherst**

Ph.D. in Computer Science

2020.9 - 2024.7

- Dissertation: "Optimization with intrinsic diversity: Towards generalizable, safe, and openended learning".
- Committee: Lee Spector (Chair), Scott Niekum, Subhransu Maji, Jeff Clune.

### **Massachusetts Institute of Technology**

Graduate Study in EECS (non-degree)

2019.9 - 2020.1

#### **University of Rochester**

M.S. in Computational Science

2016.6 - 2017.5

• Advisor: Chenliang Xu

Google

#### Work

# EXPERIENCE

Machine Learning Engineer

2024.7 - present

- Contributed to various Gemini post-training efforts, including performance optimization, model compatibility, and quality/safety evaluation.
- Led the development of Gemini models in PyTorch, optimizing it for efficient inference and fine-tuning on various hardware accelerators including next-generation chipsets.
- Developed novel methods for fine-tuning multimodal LLMs, focusing on unifying parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT), quantization-aware training (QAT), and multi-task learning.
- Designed evaluation pipeline for multimodal LLMs involving quality and safety tests.

#### **Massachusetts Institute of Technology**

Research Engineer

2017.9 - 2020.6

- Developed novel methods in deep learning for video scene segmentation, led the development of the MIT DriveSeg dataset for autonomous driving scene segmentation.
- Developed a multi-task computer vision framework for joint face landmark detection and cognitive state assessment, improving both performance and efficiency.

# SELECTED PUBLICATIONS GOOGLE SCHOLAR

- R. Boldi, <u>L. Ding</u>, L. Spector, and S. Niekum, "Pareto-optimal learning from preferences with hidden context," *preprint (under review)*, *arXiv:2406.15599*, 2024
  - POPL learns Pareto-optimal policies/rewards in RLHF, catering diverse group preferences without needing group labels, thus offers safe and fair alignment of RL agents and LLMs.
- L. Ding, J. Zhang, J. Clune, L. Spector, and J. Lehman, "Quality diversity through human feedback: Towards open-ended diversity-driven optimization," in *ICML & NeurIPS: ALOE* Workshop (Spotlight), 2024
  - QDHF learns diversity metrics from human feedback and optimizes exploration of novel solutions, enhancing task-solving of RL agents and creativity of generative models.

- L. Ding, E. Pantridge, and L. Spector, "Probabilistic lexicase selection," in *GECCO*, 2023
- <u>L. Ding</u>, J. Terwilliger, and *et al.*, "CLERA: A unified model for joint cognitive load and eye region analysis in the wild," *ACM Trans. Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI)*, 2023
- <u>L. Ding</u> and L. Spector, "Optimizing neural networks with gradient lexicase selection," in *ICLR*, 2022
- <u>L. Ding</u> and L. Spector, "Evolutionary quantum architecture search for parametrized quantum circuits," in *GECCO Companion*, 2022
- L. Ding, J. Terwilliger, R. Sherony, B. Reimer, and L. Fridman, "Value of temporal dynamics information in driving scene segmentation," *IEEE Trans. Intelligent Vehicles (T-IV)*, 2021
- <u>L. Ding</u> and C. Xu, "Weakly-supervised action segmentation with iterative soft boundary assignment," in *CVPR*, 2018

#### INTERNSHIPS Google

*Research Intern* 2023.6 - 2023.9

• Developed a JAX optimizer for efficient neural architecture search of foundation models through knowledge distillation and meta-learning.

# **CarperAI**

Student Researcher 2023.2 - 2023.6

• Proposed novel algorithms to enhance the creativity of generative models through RLHF, leading to more diverse and open-ended model behavior.

#### Meta

Research Scientist Intern 2022.5 - 2022.8

• Developed vision transformers architectures and transfer learning methods for AR/VR.

HONORS AND	Google Research Travel Scholarship (NeurIPS), Google.
AWARDS	SOAR (Supporting Open Access Research) Fund, UMass Amherst.
	4th Place (among 150 teams, top 3%), MIT Miniplaces Challenge.

2023 2019

Graduate School Scholarship (\$30,000), *University of Rochester*.

2016

2023

Meritorious Winner (top 5% worldwide), COMAP's Mathematical Contest In Modeling. 2015

TEACHING TA for MIT 6.S094: Deep Learning for Self-Driving Cars.

2018 - 2019 2018

TA for MIT 6.S099: Artificial General Intelligence. Co-instructor (w/ Tom Bertalan) for MIT Robocar Workshop.

2018

SERVICES

Reviewer for ICLR, NeurIPS, ICML, JMLR, CVPR, ICCV, ECCV, *etc*. Ph.D. Admissions Committee (UMass Amherst CICS).

2024

2020 - present

OPEN SOURCE

pyribs: an open-source library for diversity-driven optimization.

**PROJECTS** 

• Contributed the code, demo, and tutorial for QDHF.

mit-deep-learning: MIT Deep Learning Open Courses (10k+ stars).

• Main contributor for tutorials and coding assignments.

MIT AI Podcast: now the Lex Fridman Podcast, 4M+ subscribers on Youtube.

• Helped find candidates and prepare interview materials in early episodes.

SKILLS Python, C++, PyTorch, JAX, Tensorflow, Git, LLM workflows (instruction-tuning, RLHF, PEFT, quantization).